Feenie Ziner Papers 1998.0220
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Feenie Ziner Papers
1933-1988
1998.0220
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
10.5 Linear feet
The personal and professional papers of Feenie Ziner, author and professor of English at the University of Connecticut. Materials include fan mail, personal and public correspondence, teaching notes, published and unpublished manuscripts, and personal planners, calenders, and notes.
Ziner, Feenie
Biography
Florence "Feenie" Katz was born in Brooklyn, New York to first-generation Americans. Educated in the New York public school system Feenie continued her education in New York, attending Brooklyn College for her Bachelor's degree. She meet her future husband, Zeke Ziner, near her family's summer home in Peekskill, New York in the late 1930s, and shortly before the start of the second World War the two were married. As Zeke entered military service in late 1941 Feenie returned to school, attending Columbia University's School of Social Work where she was awarded a Master's degree in 1944.
Following the war Zeke and Feenie moved to Chicago where Zeke attended the Institute of Design, becoming successful as a commercial and fine arts artist, and Feenie began work as a psychiatric social worker. Finding that she could not continue psychiatric work Feenie soon tried her hand at writing, starting first with children's books. Her first few books were successful, eventually selling more than half a million copies of her first book alone. Prompted by the birth of triplets in 1958 the family moved to Dobbs Ferry, New York where Zeke started a promising new job, and Feenie continued to write children's books. Shortly after the move however, Feenie wrote her first novel for adults and quickly began to produce numerous others. With a new job in 1966 Zeke and the Ziner family would spend the next four years in Montreal, a move that allowed Feenie the opportunity to teach for the first time, in addition to continuing her writing career.
Moving back to Dobbs Ferry, Connecticut in 1970, Feenie used her teaching success in Montreal to begin writing book reviews for The New York Times, while also beginning a teaching position at the State University of New York in Purchase, New York. Teaching the contemporary novel at SUNY, Feenie was quickly offered a position in the English Department at the University of Connecticut. Intending it to be a temporary position, Feenie spent the next twenty years at UConn retiring in 1994. While at the university she taught courses in children's literature and mythology, while continuing to write for scholarly journals and The New York Times, in addition to her own novels. Feenie died on Dec. 13, 2012.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center in 1999 by Feenie Ziner.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Scope and Content Note
The papers consist primarily of correspondence, fan mail, manuscripts, magazines, calenders, planners, notes, books, and various other materials related to Feenie Ziner's personal and professional life. The papers are divided into eight boxes, each containing a mixture of materials. The boxes include correspondence between Ziner and her family and friends, fan mail she received for books she had written, manuscripts of books she both published and abandoned, as well as teaching syllabi and notes. Other materials include teacher evaluations she received from students while at the University of Connecticut, political writings and materials, and newspaper articles about herself. The papers are comprised of materials from the 1930s to the 1980s, but are not arranged in chronological order or by any particular subject.
Administrative records.; Books.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Manuscripts.; Maps.; Notes.; Photographs.; Publications.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- Series I: Inventory, 1933-1988
  - Correspondence, sound recordings (audiocassette), administrative records (incl. **Passports and IDs), clippings, financial records, maps, preliminary sketch, manuscripts, works of art, fliers, 1968-1984 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Montreal, Canada, American Writers, Fiction Writers.]
  - Manuscripts, books, clippings, notes, publications, correspondences, transcripts (speeches), 1937-1981 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: Fiction Writers, Short Stories, Plays, Academic Writing, History and Psychology (course notes).]
  - Books, notes, clippings, financial records, photographs, publications, manuscripts, correspondence, 1951-1968 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: State University of New York, Canada, American Writers, Nonfiction, Grand Banks.]
  - Correspondence, clippings, fliers, works of art, books, publications, sound recordings (L.P. record), postcards, manuscripts, 1958-1976 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Personal Letters, Reviews (of fiction), inventions.]
  - Manuscripts, sound recordings (audiocassette), books (1), notes, fliers, 1933-1980 (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Fiction Drafts.]
  - Correspondence, manuscripts, postcards, clippings, notes, 1948-1988 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Fiction Drafts, Autobiography, Historical Fiction, American History.]
  - Maps ( Vancouver, Canada), publications, fliers, books (daily planners), manuscripts, notes, 1971-1978 (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Vancouver, Canada, Fiction Drafts.]
  - Scrapbooks (1, containing clippings), clippings, correspondences, galley proofs, manuscripts, notes, maps ( Vancouver, Canada), postcards, awards, 1967-1981 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Creative Writing Classes, University of Connecticut English Department, Vancouver, Canada.]
  - Correspondence, photographs, clippings, manuscripts, postcards, notes, ephemera, publications, 1973-1984 (Box 9)
    [Subjects include: American Writers, Personal Letters, Switzerland, Fiction Drafts.]